<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A pill to purge out poperie: or, A catechisme for Romish Catholikes shewing that popery is contrarie to the grounds of the Catholike religion, and that therefore papists cannot be good Catholikes.</title>
            <author>Mico, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17858</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121915</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857072</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857072</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22743</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22743)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1606:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A pill to purge out poperie: or, A catechisme for Romish Catholikes shewing that popery is contrarie to the grounds of the Catholike religion, and that therefore papists cannot be good Catholikes.</title>
                  <author>Mico, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 45, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Beniamin Fisher: and are to be sold at his shop in Pater-noster Row at the signe of the Talbot,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By John Mico.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A pill to purge out popery.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Tightly bound.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22743:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22743:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22743:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PILL TO PVRGE OVT POPERIE: OR, A Catechiſme for Romiſh Catholikes; Shewing that Popery is contrarie to the grounds of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like RELIGION, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Papiſts cannot be good CATHOLIKES.</p>
            <p>LONDON, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rinted for <hi>Beniamin Fiſher:</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pater-noſter</hi> Row at the Signe of the Talbot. 1623.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:22743:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22743:3"/>
            <head>A PILL TO PVRGE OVT POPERIE: OR, A Catechiſme for Romiſh Catholikes; Shewing that Popery is contrarie to the grounds of the Catholike Religion, and that therefore Papiſts cannot be good CATHOLIKES.</head>
            <p>The Speakers.
<list>
                  <item>A weake Chriſtian</item>
                  <item>A Miniſter.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE I.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chriſtian.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong the diuerſities of opinions that are in the world, how may I know which is the truth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to J muſt cleaue, and who are the true Church, and true Catholikes?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Miniſter.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="a" place="bottom">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1.</note> Beleeue not euery ſpirit (that is, euery doctrine, which men bragging of the Spirit doe teach) but try them whether they be of God or no;<note n="b" place="bottom">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21.</note> Examine all things, hold faſt that which is good,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whereby ſhall I try them?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>By the Scriptures, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am vnlearned, and the Scriptures are hard to be vnderſtood.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>There are indeed many things in them, hard to bee
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22743:4"/>
vnderſtood: 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16. but ſuch things as are neceſſarie to be knowne of all to ſaluation, are plainely ſet downe, <hi>Prou.</hi> 8.9. The meaning of which place is this:</p>
                  <p>The Word of God, in points neceſſarie to ſaluation, is eaſie vnto all that haue a deſire vnto it. Turne to the places of Scripture, added to euery anſwere of the Catechiſme, and you ſhall finde this to be moſt true.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is there no other way and meanes, whereby to try and know the truth and the true profeſſors thereof?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, it may be done euen by the aforeſaid grounds of Religion. Whatſoeuer doctrine is agreeable thereunto, is true, and to be receiued: but whatſoeuer is contrary to the ſame, is falſe, and to be reiected. As many as do ſincerely and ſoundly imbrace, profeſſe, and practiſe the ſame, they are the Catholike Church, (that is, parts and members of the Catholike Church) and true Catholikes indeed. But ſuch as teach, profeſſe, and practiſe things contrary thereunto, are not the true Church, nor true Catholikes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Papiſts ſay that they onely are the true Church, and true Catholikes, and that we are not.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>So the Iewes cryed:<note n="a" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Ieremy</hi> 7.4.</note> The Temple of the Lord:<note n="b" place="bottom">
                        <hi>Ioh.</hi> 8.33, 41.</note> We are the ſeed of <hi>Abraham:</hi> the children of God.</p>
                  <p>But Chriſt told them they were the children of the diuell, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.44.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Are not the Papiſts then good Catholikes?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>No: but rather groſſe Heretikes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What is an Hereticke?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>One that doth erre in any fundamentall point of Chriſtian Religion, and doth obſtinately teach, maintaine, and defend the ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe the Papiſts erre in the fundamentall points of Religion?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>They doe teach and maintaine many falſe opinion againſt the very grounds of Religion; as by and by ſhall be ſhewed in many particulars.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:22743:4"/>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Are all Papiſts then Hereticks?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>No: for there are (no doubt) many of them that doe erre of ſimplicitie and ignorance, and which would bee brought from their errours, if they had the meanes, namely, the Scriptures in their owne language, preaching, catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, and the like. We doe not therefore account them all Hereticks, but onely thoſe before mentioned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How doe you proue that they are not good Catholicks?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>I proue it thus: They are good Catholicks, which are of ſound faith, and good life. (<hi>Aug. lib. quaeſt. in Mat. Chap.</hi> 11.) but Papiſts are neither of ſound faith, nor good life: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are no good Catholikes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How doe you proue that they are not of ſound faith?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen by the Apoſtles Creed (which may ſerue in ſtead of a rule, whereunto the faith of all men ought to agree) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary whereunto they teach many things.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shew me wherein.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The Creed is a confeſſion of faith, containing the ſumme of the Goſpell, and of ſuch things as are neceſſary to be beleeued of all that will be ſaued. They haue deuiſed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other new Articles of faith, beſides, and contrary to the Articles of the Apoſtles Creed: which they hold neceſſarily to be beleeued of all that will be ſaued: As namely, Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences and a treaſurie of Saints merits, the reall preſence, the Popes Supremacie, Purgatorie, and ſuch like. In the Councell of Trent, the curſe <hi>Anathema</hi> is pronounced vpon all ſuch as deny theſe or any of them, Maſter <hi>Perkins</hi> firſt Vol. page 621. The Creed teacheth what euery one in particular is to know and beleeue: and a true faith cannot ſtand with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out certaine knowledge. The Papiſts maintaine an impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, or an ignorant faith; namely, that it is enough to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue as the Church beleeueth: though they know not what the Church is, nor what the Church beleeueth. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hey commend this faith by the example of an old deuout <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther, a Colliar, who being tempted of the Diuell, and as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22743:5"/>
how he beleeued; anſwered, That hee beleeued as the Church beleeued: being asked againe how the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, he anſwered, As I beleeue: whereupon, the Diuell (as they ſay) was faine to depart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It ſhould ſeeme it was but a ſimple Diuell: for if hee had beene wiſe, he would haue asked him this queſtion; What if the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that thou art a foole; what would the Colliar thinke you, haue an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered then?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>I thinke he would haue ſaid nothing: for if he ſhould haue ſaid, I beleeue ſo too, the diuell might then haue beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him for a foole indeed. And yet ſuch fooles are the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ignorant Papiſts, which content themſelues with this kinde of faith: for thus one may reaſon with them; You are to beleeue as the Church beleeueth: but the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeues that you are fooles: therefore you are to beleeue ſo too. This their implicite faith euery one of himſelfe may haue. The diuels in ſome ſence may bee ſaid to haue a better faith then this: for they know what is contained in the Scriptures, and beleeue it to be true, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.19. This fond and ridiculous kind of faith, is a notable meanes to muzzle people in blindneſſe, ſuperſtition and perpetuall ignorance. Againe, faith is a certaine and true perſwaſion of the heart, whereby wee are perſwaded, and in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure aſſured of the forgiueneſſe of our ſinnes, and eternall ſaluation. The Papiſts ſay, It is preſumption to bee aſſured of ſaluation, and will haue men to doubt thereof: the which is contrary to the nature of true faith. They call the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of remiſſion of ſinnes, a faithleſſe perſwaſion: and the faith of diuels, not of Apoſtles, <hi>Concil. Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.12, 13. <hi>Rhemiſts Annot.</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>Sect.</hi> 9.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 2.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shew me, I pray you, what things in particular they teach c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rary to any Article of the Creed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:22743:5"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>I could ſhew you many, but I feare that then I ſhould be tedious to you: I will therefore ſet downe onely the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt. In the ſecond &amp; third Article is deſcribed and ſet forth vnto vs both the perſon and office of our Mediator, namely, that he is both God and man, a Prophet, Prieſt, and King.</p>
                  <p>Concerning his perſon, although in words they confeſſe him to be God and man, yet in deed they deny it: for they aſcribe to him a body inuiſible and infinite: they teach that he is corporally preſent in infinite places at once, which is proper onely to God, and contrary to the nature of a true body. And ſo in effect they doe euen deny his Man-hood. The Sonne of God is called Ieſus, becauſe hee is a Sauiour, yea the onely and perfect Sauiour which ſaueth vs from our ſinnes: that is, hath deliuered vs not onely from the blame, or guiltineſſe, but fully alſo from the puniſhment due to our ſinnes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25.</p>
                  <p>The Papiſts teach, that there muſt alſo ſome ſatisfaction of our owne come to make vp our perfect Redemption, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 14.6.8. <hi>Can.</hi> 11.15. They will not be ſaued only by IESVS CHRIST, but by the merits alſo of Saints, their owne merits, Popes pardons, &amp;c. yea, they aſcribe that to others, which is proper to Chriſt alone, and ſo conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make them their Sauiours: As for example.</p>
                  <p>They aſcribe to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Francis</hi> the ſame titles, properties, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and the very ſame office due to Ieſus Chriſt, and in all reſpects they make him like to Chriſt: whatſoeuer Chriſt did, that (as they ſay) did S. <hi>Francis.</hi> And what is this in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but to make him their Sauiour? That they doe aſcribe the former things to S. <hi>Francis,</hi> is to be ſeene, in a Booke written on purpoſe, to ſhewe the conformity betweene him &amp; Chriſt, called [The Conformitie of <hi>Francis</hi>] the which hath bin confirmed by the authority of the Church of Rome. Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Ninth, enioyned the faithfull to hold, and firmely to beleeue the things taught in the ſaid booke concerning S. <hi>Francis,</hi> and that he ſhould be puniſhed as an Hereticke, that would thinke the contrary. <hi>Confor. F.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Fol.</hi> 3.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:22743:6"/>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To whom elſe doe they aſcribe that which is proper to</hi> IESVS CHRIST?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>To the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> They deſcribe her nature by her name <hi>(Maria,)</hi> conſiſting of fiue letters, and theſe (as they ſay) doe import the fiue offices to be exerciſed by her toward vs. The firſt is <hi>Maternitatis,</hi> of Mother-hood: ſignified by the letter <hi>M:</hi> for ſhee (as they ſay) is the Mother of mercy, through whom we obtaine mercy. Her ſecond office is <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruationis,</hi> of conſeruing the treaſure of God: ſignified by the letter <hi>A:</hi> which repreſenteth <hi>Arcam theſauri,</hi> the cheſt of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: for in her (as they ſay) we ſhall find an infinite treaſure of the wiſedome and grace of God. Her third office is, <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectionis &amp; gubernationis,</hi> of direction and gouerning by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of her life. This is imported by the letter <hi>R.</hi> and therefore ſhe is named <hi>Regina,</hi> the Queene. Her fourth office is, <hi>Iacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationis, &amp; repulſionis inimicorum,</hi> of flinging and repelling backe of enemies: ſignified by the letter <hi>I:</hi> and therefore they pray thus to her: <hi>Tu nos ab hoſte protege, &amp; hora mortis ſuſcipe.</hi> Protect thou vs from the enemy, and receiue vs at the houre of death.</p>
                  <p>Her laſt office is <hi>Aduocationis,</hi> of Aduocation, imported by the letter <hi>A.</hi> From whence they pray thus: O our Aduocate, turne thy mercifull eyes vnto vs. And what doe they here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but euen place her in the roome of Ieſus, and make her their Sauiour? Theſe be the very words of Fryer <hi>Iohn Vigue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> (a Doctor, yea and a publike profeſſour of Diuinitie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them) in his Inſtitutions to his Catholike Theologie, <hi>Cap.</hi> 20. <hi>Sect.</hi> 9. <hi>Fol.</hi> 214. And herein he is like to ſuch as can make Bells to ſound, euen what pleaſeth their phantaſticall braine, and as beſt may feede their ſuperſtitious humours.</p>
                  <p>Further they ſay, That ſhe is the originall of our ſaluation, the recouerer of grace and forgiueneſſe, our hope, our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, reſurrection, &amp;c. yea that to her it is giuen to bruiſe the Serpents head, that ſhe hath done it, and procured that peace betweene God and man, which no man could procure, <hi>Viguerius ibid.</hi> 214. 215. <hi>Confor. Fran. in conclus. Lib.</hi> 1. Is not this to make her a Sauiour?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:22743:6"/>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Surely yes: and J thinke it moſt horrible blaſphemie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Account you this blaſphemy? what ſay you then to that which <hi>Carolus Scribanius,</hi> a Ieſuite, hath written of her? As namely, Firſt, that the milke of <hi>Mary</hi> may come into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon with the bloud of Chriſt. Secondly, that the Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s faith may lawfully take hold of both as wel as one. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the beſt compound for a ſicke ſoule, is to mixe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther her milke and Chriſts bloud. Fourthly, that the ſinnes and ſpirituall diſeaſes of the ſoule, are cured aſwell by her milke as by his bloud. Fifthly, that her milke and the merit and vertue of it, is more precious and excellent then Chriſts bloud. Theſe moſt horrible blaſphemies, with many ſuch like, are to bee found in the aforeſaid Ieſuites booke: which <hi>M. C.</hi> hath put into Engliſh, and ſufficiently anſwered, calling it, [The Ieſuites Goſpell] beſides all theſe things, in a booke called the Ladies Pſalter, they haue put out the word Lord, and put in the word Lady. As for example, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 110.1.</p>
                  <p>The Lord ſaid vnto our Lady, Sit thou mother at my right hand, &amp;c. The like they doe in the reſt of the Pſalmes. And is not this good ſtuffe, thinke you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe bookes were written long agone, and it may be that they are now reiected by the Papiſts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The later of them was indeede written long agone, but is not reiected, but ſtands vncontrouled, or rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by the Ieſuites, and thoſe of the principall. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meh was written but lately. And whereas both the Author and his booke (as <hi>M.C.</hi> ſaith) deſerued the fire and halter, it was ſo farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being miſliked in the Romane Sinagogue, or any way cenſured, that the booke hath bin reprinted, &amp; the Author and his booke ſtand enrolled, approued, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended (in their great volumes ſet out for that purpoſe) for good and Catholike. As they place S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Francis</hi> and the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> in Chriſts roome, ſo doe they the Pope alſo: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ribing that to him, which is proper vnto Ieſus Chriſt, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay not (without blaſphemy) be aſcribed to any creature. They ſay that the Pope is the Sun: The Church the Moone.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22743:7"/>
The Pope is the Bridegroome: the Church the Bride. The Pope is the head: the Church the body. And what is this, but to place the Pope in the roome of Ieſus Chriſt; and euen to ſay that the Pope is Chriſt? <hi>Confor. F.</hi> 2. <hi>li.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 10. That they doe thus place S. <hi>Francis,</hi> the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and the Pope in Chriſts roome, and ſo make them Sauiours, is more at large, and ſufficiently proued (out of their owne Writers) in a little Treatiſe (ſet forth by M. <hi>Thomas Rogers</hi> in the yeere 1589.) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, An hiſtoricall Dialogue of Antichriſt and Popery.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 3.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hitherto you haue ſhewed, how the Son of God is called</hi> Ieſus, <hi>becauſe he is a Sauiour, and how the Papiſts do place others in his roome: Now ſhew me alſo why he is called</hi> Chriſt, <hi>&amp; what that title ſignifieth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſignifieth, <hi>Anointed:</hi> which title ſetteth forth his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: namely, that he is our only true Prophet, Prieſt &amp; King.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe they teach any thing contrary hereunto?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>They doe euen deny this Office of his, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, deny the fruits of his comming in the fleſh, 1. <hi>Iob.</hi> 4.3</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shew me wherein they deny his Office.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Chriſt is a Prophet to teach his Church, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale the will of God vnto vs, to whom all are to hearken, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10.27. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.22, 23. And this hee hath perfectly done in the Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>They preferre their owne blinde traditions before the Scriptures: they lay aſide the Scriptures, accounting and calling them dumbe Iudges, A noſe of Waxe, The blacke Goſpell, Inken diuinitie, &amp;c. <hi>Piggius Contr.</hi> 3. <hi>de Eccl. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarch. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. A certaine popiſh Doctor reaſoning with M. <hi>Tindal,</hi> was not aſhamed to ſay, that we were better to be without Gods Law then the Popes. They likewiſe ſet vp Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to be Lay-mens bookes, and ſo in all this they deny by conſequence his Propheticall office. Chriſt is alſo a Prieſt, and that for euer, after the order of <hi>Melchſedech, Heb.</hi> 7.24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And in this his office he hath none to ſucceede him. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> acknowledge not this, but maintaine ſtill an outward an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> corporall Prieſthood, to offer vp an outward ſacrifice, eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:22743:7"/>
Chriſt himſelfe, <hi>Rhem.</hi> on <hi>Heb. chap.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.8.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If this were true, why then, the Prieſt were become a Mediator betweene God and Chriſt: the which is moſt abſurd, to thinke that any creature ſhould be ſuch a one.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>It is indeed moſt abſurd: and yet in the very Canon of the Maſſe they intimate thus much, when they requeſt God to accept their gifts and offerings (namely, Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe offered) as he did the ſacrifices of <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Noah.</hi> And which is more abſurd than this, (yea blaſphemy for any to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme) they (by their former doctrine) doe make the Prieſt to be more worthy, in ſome reſpect, then Chriſt: for the perſon that doth offer a ſacrifice, is of more worth &amp; honour then the thing which he offereth; but the Prieſt (as they ſay) offereth vp Chriſt to God his Father: therefore the Prieſt that offereth him, is of more worth and honour then Chriſt, whom he offereth.</p>
                  <p>As Chriſt is a Prieſt, ſo he alone, (and that but once for all) offered himſelfe: and by his one offering once offered, hath made a full and perfect ſatisfaction for all our ſinnes, ſo that now there remaineth no more offering for ſinnes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12, 14, 26, 10, 14, 18. They teach that in the Maſſe, there is dayly a ſacrifice offered for the ſinnes both of the quick and the dead: and ſo they make Chriſts ſacrifice not to bee the perfect and onely ſacrifice of the New Teſtament, but ſet vp another in ſtead thereof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They ſay that their ſacrifice is not a new ſacrifice, or another from Chriſts, but that it is the ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The Author to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> teacheth, that Chriſts ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice neither may, nor ought to bee reiterated &amp; repeated: for as it is but one, ſo it was but once offered. And this word (Once) he vſeth fiue ſeuerall times, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.27, 9, 12, 26, 28, 30.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They ſay that Chriſt indeed was offered but once after a bloudy manner: but he is often offered after an vnbloudy manner.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>This diſtinction of theirs hath no warrant out of Gods Word: nay rather it is directly againſt the Word: for, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. it is ſaid, Almoſt all things are by the Law purged with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22743:8"/>
bloud: and without ſhedding of bloud is no remiſſion. From whence we may thus reaſon, Without ſhedding of bloud is no remiſsion: but in the Maſſe is no ſhedding of bloud: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no remiſsion. And therefore it is no ſacrifice for ſinne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Though this their diſtinction bee not to bee found in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, yet it is in the writings of the Fathers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The Fathers indeed make mention of vnbloudy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices: but they hereby vnderſtand not outward and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Sacrifices for ſinne, but the Spiritual Sacrifices of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; and they ſo call them, in comparing them with the bloudy ſacrifices of the Law, &amp; with Chriſts bloudy ſacrifice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Papiſts doe not ſay that the ſacrifice of the Maſſe is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piatorie, but an applicatorie ſacrifice: that is, it ſerues not properly to make any ſatisfaction to God, but rather to apply vnto vs the ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt already made.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Their doctrine is, that it is a ſacrifice propitiatory: that is, auaileable to obtaine (<hi>ex opere operato,</hi> by the very work wrought) remiſsion &amp; pardon of all their ſinnes: yea, that it is auailable to obtaine all other benefits; as peace, health, and ſuch like, <hi>Concil. Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 22. <hi>Can.</hi> 3. <hi>Bellar. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de Miſſ. cap.</hi> 25. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. But let it be (as you ſay) that they account it but an applicatory ſacrifice, yet this maketh nothing for them. The Sacrifices of the Law did ſerue to apply the vertue of Chriſts Croſſe: and yet the Apoſtle excludeth them by this reaſon; that where there is remiſsion of ſinnes, there is no more Sacrifice, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.18. Wherefore if the Apoſtles reaſon be good, it concludeth alſo againſt their Sacrifice applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. Againe, the Apoſtle teacheth, that therefore the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of the Law are aboliſhed by the death of Chriſt; becauſe they were but ſhadowes of good things to come, and could not make the offerers perfect, &amp;c. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1, 2, 3. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, this kinde of applying ſacrifice (which they faine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues) hath ceaſed. We need not now a Sacrifice for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of Chriſts death: for Chriſt to that end hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the preaching of the Word, and hath inſtituted Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, whereby his death, with all the benefits thereof,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22743:8"/>
are moſt fruitfully applied vnto vs, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, this their applying ſacrifice, is againſt the nature of a Sacrament, in which God giues Chriſt vnto vs: whereas in a ſacrifice God receiues from man, and man giues ſomething to God.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ancient Fathers vſed to call the Supper of the Lord, a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: it ſhould ſeeme therefore, that there is ſome ſacrifice offered therein to God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true that they called it ſo: not that Chriſt is therein offered a Sacrifice to God, but in other reſpects. Firſt, becauſe that therein there was an offering and giuing of almes, bread, wine, &amp;c. which are a Spirituall Sacrifice. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, they called the Sacrament, a Sacrifice, not properly, but figuratiuely: becauſe there was therein a repreſentation of that Sacrifice which was offered vpon the Croſſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a commemoration of Chriſts body, which he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs, and of his bloud which he ſhed for vs. Thirdly, It is called a ſacrifice, becauſe it is an application of the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice offered vpon the Croſſe, vnto our ſelues. Fourthly, It is ſo called, becauſe of the ſacrifice of prayers &amp; thanksgiuings: and becauſe in the Lords Supper we offered our ſelues vnto God to be conſecrated vnto him, and ſerue him in body and ſoule.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What is then your opinion of the Popiſh Maſſe?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>It is an abbridgement of all ſuperſtition and idolatry: there is in it adoration directed to bread: there is (as they ſay) the body of Chriſt offered really in a ſacrifice of propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation: which was neuer offered but once with ſhedding of bloud. There is adoration of ſtocks &amp; ſtones, inuocation of dead men, ſaying of Maſſes to the honour of Saints &amp; Angels, worſhipping of dead mens bones, &amp; ſuch like abominations.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the Maſſe be ſuch an idoll, and ſo contrarie to Chriſts ſacrifice, whence had it then its firſt beginning?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The Maſſe had this originall: Firſt, the Lords Supper was celebrated in moſt ſimple &amp; plaine manner. Secondly, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>egan to admit ſome increaſe of ceremonies, eſpecially the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22743:9"/>
offrings for the dead, which was but a thanksgiuing for them, vntill more then two hundred yeeres after Chriſt. Thirdly, prayers for the dead, got entrance into the Lords Supper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the yeere foure hundred: and then came in Purgatory, and the redemption of ſoules from thence by Maſſes, M. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> 2. <hi>Vol.</hi> 554. 1. <hi>D.</hi> Againe, you are to know that the Maſſe is like a beggers cloake, patcht vp with many pieces, whereof ſome were put in at one time, ſome at another. One Pope puts in one patch, another Pope puts in another: and it was not fully patcht vp, as now it is, till twelue hundred yeeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt, Acts and Monuments, <hi>pag.</hi> 1274. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And in the Canon of the Maſſe, there are to bee found a full halfe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of errours and blaſphemies, <hi>Synopſis Papiſmi,</hi> the 13. ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall controuerſie, <hi>queſt.</hi> 8.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But how can the Maſse bee ſo late and now, ſeeing that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in their writings make mention of it?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The word <hi>(Miſsa)</hi> (which is now called the Maſſe) in the Fathers, ſignifieth a publike meeting to the communion, and to prayers, or the ſolemne diſmiſſion of that meeting, or euen the forme of their religious worſhip. And the Phraſe <hi>Miſſam facere,</hi> (vſed in ſome of the Fathers) doth not ſignifie to ſay the Popiſh Maſſe, but to diſmiſſe ſome out of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly. After the Sermon the Catechumeniſts, (that is, ſuch as learned the Catechiſme, and were not yet admitted to the Lords Supper) are diſmiſſed. And hereupon the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was called <hi>Miſsa</hi> figuratiuely, becauſe when it began, there was a diſmiſſion of ſome, <hi>Perkins</hi> 2. Vol. 552. 2. <hi>D.</hi> 553. <hi>Synop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis Papiſmi.</hi> the 13. generall Controuerſie, <hi>Queſt</hi> 2.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am ſatisfied touching the Sacrifice of the Maſſe, by which (as I doe now plainely perceiue) they doe euen deny the Prieſthood, and the onely ſacrifice of Chriſt: I pray you now to ſhew me wherein elſe they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny his Prieſthood?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Chriſts Prieſthood conſiſteth of two parts, Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Interceſſion. As by his owne Sacrifice once offered, he hath made a perfect ſatisfaction for our ſinnes: ſo he now continually maketh interceſſion to God for vs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.34<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. The Papiſts teach, that the Saints in Heauen do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:22743:9"/>
make interceſſion to God for particular men, according to their ſeuerall wants: and that hauing receiued particular mens prayers, they preſent them vnto God. And ſo herein they doe alſo deny the Office of Chriſts Prieſt hood, <hi>Rhem.</hi> on <hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. on 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. on 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. and in many other places.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They ſay that Chriſt indeed is the onely Mediator of Redemptions but the Saints are alſo Mediatours of Interceſsion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>This is but an idle diſtinction: for Chriſt onely is the Mediatour as well of the one as the other. For in a true and ſufficient Mediatour, there muſt be theſe properties: firſt of all, the Word of God muſt reueale and propound him vnto the Church. Secondly, he muſt be perfectly iuſt, and ſuch a one as in whom was no ſinne euer found. Thirdly, hee muſt be a Propitiator, that is, bring ſome thing to God, that may appeaſe and ſatisfie his wrath &amp; iuſtice for our ſinnes. Now, theſe three properties are not to be found in any creature, but in Chriſt alone: and therefore he is the onely Mediator of Interceſſion, as well as of Redemption, <hi>Perkins</hi> 1. <hi>Volume.</hi> 603. 604.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Do they teach any thing contrary to the Kingly office of Chriſt?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, they teach that the Pope is Chriſts Vicar, &amp; head of the Church; that hee can make Lawes to binde the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; that he can make new Articles, and aboliſh the old; that he can diſpenſe with al the precepts both of the old and new Teſtament: And ſo herein (and in many other ſuch like things) they deny the Kingly Office of Chriſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It ſeemeth then to me (by this which you haue ſaid) that though in words they confeſſe Chriſt, yet in deed and in truth they deny him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>They doe ſo indeed: for whoſoeuer denyeth the office of Chriſt, (for the performance whereof he came in the fleſh) denyeth in effect, Chriſt to be come in the fleſh: but the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts deny his office, therefore they deny him to be come in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he fleſh: &amp; ſo they are no good Catholikes, but rather Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ikes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What ſhould mooue the Church of Rome in words to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:22743:10"/>
CHRIST, <hi>and yet to deny his office?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>It makes much for her profit, and by this meanes they doe the more eaſily deceiue people. That their profit and aduantage is the onely end they aime at, appeareth by a moſt blaſphemous ſpeech of a Pope of Rome, (<hi>Leo</hi> the 10) who being ſomewhat moued againſt one of his Cardinals, for alleadging a place againſt him out of the Goſpell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Chriſt, anſwered him thus, <hi>Quantum nobis profuit iſta fabula de Chriſto?</hi> O what aduantage hath this fable of Chriſt brought vs? <hi>Sleydan de ſtatu Relig. &amp;c. Reip. lib.</hi> 1. They are herein much like to a Fowler, who ſpreading his net to catch Larkes, hath tyed to his net an artificiall Larke, a Larke in ſhew, but not indeede. This hee cauſeth to moue and ſtirre, the which the Larkes perceiuing, and thinking it to be a Larke indeede, they fall downe by him, and ſo are caught in the net. So they haue a Chriſt in their mouthes, to draw people to them, but it is a counterfeit Chirſt. Or if it be the true Chriſt, yet they doe it but as the Larke-catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er doth, who many times hath in his net a true and liuing Larke indeede, but it is to deceiue the Larkes, and the more eaſily to catch them in his net. So they profeſſe Chriſt, haue his Word and Sacraments among them, but it is onely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue ſimple people, and to make a prey of them.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 4.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe they teach any other thing, contrary to any other article of the Creede?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, diuers things. In the Article we profeſſe to be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leeue, that Chriſt was conceiued by the Holy Ghoſt: and ſo he, and he onely, was conceiued without originall ſinne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> They teach, that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was alſo conceiued withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> origin all ſinne: and that by this meanes it came to paſſe that Chriſt was free from all ſpot, <hi>Concil. Trid. Seſs.</hi> 5. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peccato originali.</hi> And ſo herein they do altogether ouerthro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this Article of Chriſts conception by the Holy Ghoſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:22743:10"/>
whoſe onely power the Scripture doth impute Chriſts holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> which was no leſſe then all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers conceiued and borne in ſinne, &amp; did need Chriſt to be her Mediator as wel as the reſt of mankind. There was a long time a foule ſtirre in the Church of Rome, betweene the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicans and the Franciſcans about this point, Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, <hi>pa.</hi> 732. It was the common opinion of Fathers and Writers vntill <hi>Lumbards</hi> time, (which was about the yeere 1150.) that ſhe was conceiued in Original ſinne, <hi>Perkins</hi> 2. <hi>Vol.</hi> 596. In the fourth Article wee profeſſe, that Chriſt ſuffered, &amp;c. by which he hath made a full and perfect ſatisfaction for the ſinnes of his elect, and for the whole puniſhment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, both eternall and temporall.</p>
                  <p>The Papiſts teach, that Chriſt hath ſatisfied for ſinnes go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before Baptiſme; but concerning ſinnes following Baptiſme, the fault is remitted by the Paſſion of Chriſt, and the puniſhment (which of infinite is made finite) is to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied for, by men themſelues, either heere or in Purgatorie: that is, men themſelues muſt ſatisfie the iuſtice of God, for the temporall puniſhment of their offences, either on earth or in Purgatorie.</p>
                  <p>There is (ſay they) a certaine infernall place in the earth, called Purgatory, in the which as in a priſon-houſe, the ſoules which were not fully purged in this life, are there clenſed and purged by fire, before they can be receiued into heauen: <hi>Bell. de Purgat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>and cap.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>Rhem. on</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>They ſay alſo, that it is an Article of faith, to beleeue that there is a Purgatorie; and that he which beleeues it not, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re to goe to hell, <hi>Bellar. ibid. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 15. But this is ſo farre from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eing an Article of faith, as that it is a meere fable, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rarie to an Article of faith. The bloud of Chriſt is the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atory of our ſinnes, 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7. Afflictions are called the fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tryall, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7.4.12. whereby wee are clenſed from our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orruption, as gold is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the droſſe by fire. No other Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rie is to be found in Scriptures. The Scriptures mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22743:11"/>
two ſorts of men, beleeuers, and vnbeleeuers; and but two places after this for them, heauen for the one, and hell for the other, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.25, 26. <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.36. <hi>Reuelation</hi> 20.14, 15.21.7, 8. They that dye in the Lord, reſt from their labours: which cannot be true, if any of them goe to Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie. Their workes follow them, that is, the reward of their workes, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.13. If any man ſhould haue gone to Purgatorie, then the thiefe vpon the Croſſe had gone thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: who repenting at his end, wanted time to make ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the temporall puniſhment of his ſinnes: but Chriſt ſaid to him, To day ſhalt thou bee with me in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. The doctrine of Purgatorie came into the Church, out of the Heathen writers, for the Philoſophers and Poets were the firſt that euer wrote of it: and Popiſh Purgatorie was vnknowne to the Fathers many hundred yeeres after Chriſt, <hi>Perkins.</hi> 2. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ol.</hi> 568.569.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If Purgatorie be but a fable, contrary to an Article of faith, then what is the cauſe that the Church of Rome ſo ſtifty maintaines it?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>There is great cauſe why they ſhould ſo doe, for it keepes in the fire in the Popes Kitchin: for, if the fire of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie were not great, the fire in the Popes Kitchin would be but ſmall; for, by this meanes they haue ſtore of money for Pardons, Maſſes, Diriges, and other ſuch like trumperies.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 5.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe they teach any thing elſe contrary to the Creede?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes: The ſixth Article ſaith, that Chriſt aſcended into Heauen, &amp;c. and the Scriptures ſay, that the Heauens muſt containe him, &amp;c. Acts. 1.11.3.21. They teach contrarie hereunto, namely, that Chriſt is corporally preſent in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sacrament, and that in many places at once: The which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> contrary to the nature of a true body, and contrarie to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nature of the Sacrament, which is a remembrance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt. <hi>Virgilius</hi> againſt <hi>Eutyches. lib.</hi> 4. ſaith thus: When <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> (that is the fleſh of Chriſt) was on earth, it was not in he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen: and becauſe it is now in Heauen, it is not on eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> This is the Catholike faith and confeſſion. It is an Arti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:22743:11"/>
of faith to beleeue the Catholike Church: and faith is the euidence of things not ſeene, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.1. Therefore the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church is alwaies vnto the world inuiſible, and not to be eſpied but by the eyes of faith: becauſe things ſeene are not beleeued. The Papiſts teach that the Catholike Church is, and hath bin alwaies viſible. <hi>Rhem.</hi> on <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. The Church is ſaid to be Catholike, that is, vniuerſall, becauſe it is not tyed to any one ſpeciall place, but is ſpred abroad ouer the face of the earth. They tye it to Rome alone, which can be but a particular Church, &amp; not vniuerſall, In the Church there is a Communion of Saints: and theſe are they that are ſanctified by the bloud and Spirit of Chriſt, hauing the perfect holines of Chriſt put vpon them, by imputation of faith, and the quality of imperfect holines powred into their heart by the Spirit of ſanctification, And ſuch are the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full here on earth, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.2.</p>
                  <p>The Papiſts acknowledge none to bee Saints, but ſuch as are in heauen, They teach that the Pope can canonize Saints: whereas to make one a Saint, is onely the worke of God, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. The Pope hath canonized many, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede were neuer true Saints of God, but wicked men, and ranke Traitours to their Princes, as <hi>Becket,</hi> with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>This canonizing of Saints was neuer heard of with the Fathers, vntill the yeere 880. and then <hi>Adrian</hi> tooke vp this authoritie. And <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, after him, confirmed it in his decrees.</p>
                  <p>In the Creede we profeſſe, to beleeue the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, that is, I beleeue that God, for Chriſt his ſake, doth freely forgiue the ſinnes of his Elect, and my ſinnes alſo. And herein conſiſteth our iuſtification, namely, in the free for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes of our ſinnes, and the imputation of Chriſts righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes to vs. The Papiſts teach many things contrary to this Article. Firſt, that men are to make ſatisfaction for their ſinnes. Now, ſatisfaction for ſinnes, and forgiuenes of ſinnes, are contraries. If we ſatisfie in our own perſon, wee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22743:12"/>
are not iuſtified freely: if we be iuſtified freely (as moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely we are, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23.) then we make no ſatisfaction at all. If a man can ſatisfie and pay a debt, then he needes no forgiueneſſe: but if the debt bee forgiuen him, then it is plaine, that there is no ſatisfaction made. The ſatisfaction for our ſinnes was made by Chriſt, and not by vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Did not the ancient Fathers teach men to make ſatisfaction for their ſinnes?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſatisfaction which they maintained, was an eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall and publike mulct, or penalty impoſed vpon noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious offenders, thereby to teſtifie their repentance, and to ſatisfie the Church whom they had offended, <hi>Perkins.</hi> 1. <hi>V.</hi> 577, <hi>&amp;c</hi> 2 <hi>vol.</hi> 165. 2 <hi>D.</hi> 166.</p>
                  <p>The efficient cauſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of our iuſtification, is God alone. It is God onely that forgiueth our ſinnes. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 43.25. <hi>Mar.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Ro.</hi> 8.33. They teach that the Pope can forgiue ſinnes, and we know that he giues pardons, not only for the time paſt, but alſo for the time to come: yea they teach that prieſts haue right to remit ſinnes, and they alleadge theſe places to proue it: <hi>Math.</hi> 16.19. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20.23. Now we are to note this, that as none can forgiue a debt, but the party to whom the debt is due: ſo none can forgiue ſinnes, but God onely, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom the ſinne is committed, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 51.4. The power of binding and looſing committed to the Apoſtles &amp; Miniſters of the Word, is, by declaring the will and pleaſure of GOD out of his Word, both to pronounce forgiuenes of ſinnes to all that are truely penitent: and the retayning of them to the impenitent. The Pope and his Clergie are neuer able to proue themſelues to bee the true Miniſters of Chriſt: and they cannot ſo much as challenge this latter authoritie and power to themſelues, much leſſe the former which is proper to God onely. The motiue or impulſiue cauſe, which moued God to iuſtifie vs, was not any thing in vs, but onely the grace of God, that is the free good will and pleaſure of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.8 <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5, 7. They teach that wee are not iuſtified by grace onely, but by workes alſo, that is, by the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22743:12"/>
merit of our works. And to this end they haue (of late yeeres) deuiſed a firſt &amp; ſecond Iuſtification. The firſt is, when a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (of an euill man) is made a good man: and this (they ſay) commeth onely of Gods mercy by the merit of Chriſt. The ſecond is, when one (of a good or iuſt man) is made better and more iuſt: and this proceedeth from workes.</p>
                  <p>But we are to know, that there are not two kinds of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, a firſt and ſecond; but one and the ſame iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, conſidered in different reſpects. In reſpect of Gods actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all acceptation of a mans perſon, iuſtification is abſolute: but in reſpect of the actuall application, and manifeſtation of Gods acceptation vnto a mans conſcience, iuſtification is by parts and degrees. (M. <hi>Scudder</hi> on the Lords Prayer, <hi>pag.</hi> 303. to 309.</p>
                  <p>And further we are to note, that the Papiſts ſecond iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is no other then ſanctification, which is an effect &amp; fruit of iuſtification: the which is imperfect, &amp; not able to iuſtifie vs before God The materiall cauſe of our iuſtification, is the actiue and paſſiue righteouſneſſe and obedience of Ieſus Chriſt, his inherent holineſſe, his fulfilling of the Law, his death, ſacrifice, and full ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>The formall cauſe, or the forme of iuſtification, is the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of Chriſt, imputed of God vnto vs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.19, 21. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.9. The Papiſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ride this doctrine, that Men are iuſtified by the imputation of the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt: which righteouſneſſe is not in vs, but in Chriſt. The <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> call it a new no-iuſtice, a phantaſticall apprehenſion of that which is not. <hi>Rhem. on Ro.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect</hi> 7. They hold them accurſed that ſo affirme and teach: And they teach, that the onely formall cauſe of our iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion, is the iuſtice of God, whereby wee are not reputed and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccounted iuſt, but are made iuſt indeed: and this iuſtice is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat which euery man hath within himſelfe, and is inherent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n him, <hi>Concil. Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 6. <hi>can.</hi> 10, 11. <hi>Rhem. on Phil. cha.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he inſtrumentall cauſe of iuſtification, on our part, is a true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd liuely faith, whereby wee receiue and apply vnto our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22743:13"/>
ſelues the mercy of God, Chriſt Ieſus and all his benefits, reſting vpon him alone for ſaluation.</p>
                  <p>They teach, that faith doth not iuſtifie, as an inſtrument in apprehending the righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, but as a proper and true cauſe, it actually iuſtifieth by the dignity, worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and meritorious worke thereof, <hi>Bellar. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de iuſtificat. cap.</hi> 17. They teach alſo, that faith is not the onely cauſe of our iuſtification, but that there are other alſo, as hope, charity, almes-deeds and other vertues: yea, they ſay, that workes are more principall then faith, in the matter of iuſtification: and pronounce him accurſed that ſhall ſay, a man is iuſtified onely by faith. <hi>Rhem. on Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Sect.</hi> 6. <hi>and on I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m.</hi> 2. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. <hi>Bellar. l.</hi> 1 <hi>de iuſtif. c.</hi> 13. <hi>Concil. Trid. Seſs.</hi> 6 <hi>Can.</hi> 9. Theſe and other ſuch like things they teach, contrary to the doctrine of iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which is a maine ground of Religion. And if there were no more points of difference betweene vs, theſe were ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to keepe vs from vniting of our Religions: for heereby the Church of Rome doth raze the very foundation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>You ſaid before, that we are iuſtified freely: I would know how this can be, if we be iuſtified by the righteouſnes, and for the merit of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Becauſe the Decree of God the Father for our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption is free, and we pay nothing againe to God of our owne. And therefore by the word (freely) our merits are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, but not Chriſts. By which it appeareth, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of our ſelues, we are iuſtified freely of Gods meere mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and grace, without any reſpect of our owne righteouſne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> or worthineſſe, but yet through Chriſt, and for his righteou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe and obedience imputed to vs: both which are ſignifie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23, 24.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shew me (I pray you what is meant by (Merit) what the dect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> of the Papiſts is concerning merit, and whether that our workes be m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>orious or no.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>By (Merit) wee vnderſtand any thing, or any worke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> whereby Gods fauour and life euerlaſting is procured; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> that for the dignitie and excellency of the worke or thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:22743:13"/>
done. Now the true merit whereby wee looke to attaine the fauour of God, and life euerlaſting, is to be found in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt alone, in whom God is well pleaſed. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts make two kindes of merit: the merit of the perſon, and the merit of the worke. The merit of the perſon is (as they ſay) a dignitie in the perſon, whereby it is worthy of life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting. The merit of the worke, is a dignitie or excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the worke, whereby it is made fit, and inabled to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue life euerlaſting for the doer of the worke. <hi>See Rhem.</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. We now doe renounce our owne perſonall me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and all merit of our owne workes, and rely onely vpon the merits of Chriſt, and we hold that no workes of ours can merit. That no man by any workes of his can merit, may bee proued by the properties and conditions that muſt bee in a worke meritorious, and they are fiue.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the worke muſt be abſolutely perfect: but all our workes are vnperfect, as well in parts, as in degrees of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment. In parts, becauſe we omit many things which the Law preſcribeth, and doe many euill things which the Law prohibiteth. In degrees, becauſe the works of the Saints are vncleane, <hi>Eſay</hi> 64.6. Phil. 3.8.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, a man muſt doe the worke of himſelfe, and by himſelfe: for if it be done by the helpe of another, the merit doth not properly belong to the dooer. But the good workes which we doe, are not ours, but are wrought by God in vs.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, a man muſt doe the worke, of his owne free will and pleaſure, not of due debt: for when we doe that which we are bound to doe, we doe no more but our duty. But whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we doe, we doe it as poore debters; nay, wee are worſe then poore debters; we are miſerable bankerupts, wee haue nothing; we haue leſſe then nothing to pay, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.10.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, the worke muſt be done to the benefit and profit of him from whom we looke to be repayed. But no man by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worke of his can bring any profit vnto God, <hi>Iob</hi> 22.2.35.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.2.50.12. We may benefit men, but we cannot benefit our Maker, from whom we haue receiued life and limb, ſoule
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22743:14"/>
and body, and all that we haue: wee can giue him nothing, and therefore can deſerue nothing from him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.35, 36.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, the worke and the reward muſt be in proportion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall: for if the reward be more then the worke, it is not then a reward of deſert, but a gift of good-will. But there is no proportion betweene our workes, which are altogether vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, and the excellency of thoſe great bleſſings, and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits which the Father giueth vs freely in his Sonne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.18. And therefore in this and the former reſpects, there can be no merit in any meere man: wherefore it is no leſſe abſurd to ſay, that we merit ſaluation at Gods hands by good works, then if one ſhould ſay, Thou haſt giuen mee an hundred pounds, therefore thou oughteſt to giue me a thouſand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Was not this doctrine of merit taught in the times of ancient Fathers?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Merit being taken in his proper ſenſe, for due &amp; iuſt deſert, was neuer allowed of the ſound Profeſſors for a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeeres after Chriſt, <hi>Perkins</hi> 1. Vol. 574, 575. ſecond Vol. 535, 536. Such therefore as will be iuſtified and ſaued by their owne workes, and challenge eternall life by their merits, doe ſhew themſelues to be moſt proud and vnthankefull perſons, and deſerue moſt iuſtly to be condemned eternally.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Papiſts at their end, doe renounce their owne merits, and profeſſe that they looke to be ſaued onely by the merits of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>If there were nothing elſe but this, it were enough to proue their doctrine of merit, to be a falſe doctrine: for if it were a truth, then a man is not onely in his life time to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it, and maintaine it, but alſo in his death; yea rather to dye for it, then to deny it. But ſeeing they in their life pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it and maintaine it, but at their death renounce it; it is a manifeſt argument, that euen they themſelues doe know, that it is not a true, but a fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e doctrine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If they know that it is not a truth, what makes them then in their life-time ſo ſtiffely to maintaine it?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſerues greatly to maintaine and vphold the Popes kingdome: for they teach, that the ouer-plus of Chriſts me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:22743:14"/>
and of the merits of Saints and Martyrs, is the treaſure of the Church, which being gathered together, and put into a ſtore-cheſt, is in the Popes cuſtodie, and he alone hath the plenary opening and ſhutting of this Cheſt, and the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and diſpoſing of theſe merits: by vertue whereof, hee giues out Indulgences and Pardons when and to whom hee will: So that ſuch as haue not merits enow of their own, may haue them from thence. And ſo hereby hee maintaines and vpholds his kingdome: for hereby comes in infinite wealth and reuenewes, <hi>Perkins</hi> 3. <hi>vol.</hi> 1. <hi>part. pag.</hi> 165 2. <hi>D.</hi> 2. <hi>vol.</hi> 590. 2. <hi>a.</hi> In theſe and many other particular points, the Papiſts teach contrary to the Articles of the Creed, and therefore are no true Catholikes, neither doe they belong to the Catholike Church, as is thus proued: Whoſoeuer haue not the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like faith, doe not belong to the Catholike Church: but the Papiſts haue not the Catholike faith; therefore they doe not belong to the Catholike Church. That they haue not the Catholike faith, is plaine by that aforegoing.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 6.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe they teach any thing contrary to the doctrine of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, many things. Chriſt ordained but onely two Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. The Church of Rome hath added to them fiue more; namely, Confirmation, Penance, Matrimonie, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eme Vnction.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Are not theſe Sacraments indeed?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſurely: for there are foure things neceſſarily requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to make a Sacrament. Firſt, the authoritie of Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding it. Secondly, the element or outward ſigne, as the matter of it. Thirdly, the word of inſtitution, as the forme. Fourthly, the end and vſe, to be a ſeale of our faith, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes. Theſe foure things are not to be found in their fiue latter Sacraments, and therefore they are no Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments indeed. <hi>Maſter Atterſoll</hi> on the Sacraments, <hi>pag.</hi> 119. to 150. <hi>Synopſis Papiſ. Controu.</hi> 14, 15, 16.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>May not the Church then inſtitute and ordaine Sacraments?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:22743:15"/>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>None may ordaine a Sacrament, but onely the Lord. As none may put a ſigne and ſeale to a mans laſt Will and Teſtament, but onely the maker of the Teſtament: ſo none may ordaine Sacraments (which are ſignes and ſeales of the new Teſtament and couenant of grace) but onely the Lord which made the couenant. And therefore the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in doing the contrary, proues her ſelfe not to bee the true Church of Chriſt, but rather the Church of Antichriſt. They doe alſo in many other things teach contrary to the doctrine of the Sacraments. As;</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that the Sacraments doe giue grace, and namely, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> by the worke wrought, <hi>Rhem. Acts</hi> 22. <hi>Sect.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that not onely faith doth iuſtifie, but the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments alſo, <hi>Rhem. Rom.</hi> 6. <hi>Sect.</hi> 5. Whereas Sacraments are ſignes and ſeales of iuſtification, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that Infants dying without Baptiſme, cannot bee ſaued, <hi>Rhem. Ioh.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 2. They haue alſo added many idle ceremonies to Baptiſme, as Creame, Tapers, Salt, &amp;c. with an opinion of ſaluation and worſhip annexed vnto them: yea in times paſt they baptized Bels, but now they begin to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of it, and ſay that they were but onely hallowed and conſecrated to holy vſes, <hi>Bellar. l.</hi> 4. <hi>de Pont. Rom. c.</hi> 12. <hi>Synopſis Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſmi, Controu</hi> 12. <hi>Queſt.</hi> 5. Concerning the Lords Supper, they haue likewiſe moſt groſſely abuſed it in many things.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, they take away the Cup from the Laity: whereas the Church of Rome for aboue a thouſand yeeres after Chriſt, vſed both ſignes in the Communion. The Communion vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one kind, was decreed, defined, and determined as a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Law in the Councell of Conſtance, about the yeere 1114. <hi>Perk.</hi> 2. Vol. 554.2. <hi>b.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, they reſerue the Bread in boxes, pixes &amp; other veſſels of the Church, for dayes, weekes, and moneths. They ſhew it to the people, the Prieſt lifting it ouer his head, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> going with it in proceſſion. All this is contrary to the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for it is no Sacrament, vnleſſe there be a giuing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22743:15"/>
eating, and drinking, M. <hi>Atterſoll</hi> on the Sacraments, 386, 387.</p>
                  <p>The reſeruation of the Sacrament was not allowed of, but rather found fault withall by the Fathers, <hi>Perk.</hi> 2. <hi>vol.</hi> 557.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, they adore, fall downe and honour the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with diuine worſhip, calling it their Lord and God. A thing neuer heard of among the heathen Idolaters, namely, to worſhip a piece of bread, or rather, a thin Wafer.</p>
                  <p>The adoration in the Sacrament belongeth vnto Chriſt ſitting in heauen: and is an inward worſhip of the heart, or lifting vp of the minde, being ſtirred vp with the outward ſignes. Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the third (in the yeere 1220.) was the firſt that euer inſtituted the adoration of the Sacrament. And after him <hi>Vrban</hi> the fourth ordained a feaſt in honour of the body of Chriſt. <hi>Perk.</hi> 2. <hi>Vol.</hi> 564. <hi>Atterſoll</hi> on the Sacraments, 388, 389.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, they turne the Sacrament into a ſacrifice for the quick &amp; the dead, aboliſhing the fruit &amp; remembrance of the death of Chriſt, diſannulling his Prieſthood, giuing him to his Father, whereas the Father hath giuen him to vs, &amp;c. <hi>ibid. page</hi> 390.</p>
                  <p>Fiftly, they maintaine Tranſubſtantiation. Theſe are their very words: If any man ſhall ſay, that there remaineth the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine in the Sacrament, after the words of conſecration, or ſhal deny that the whole ſubſtance of Bread and Wine is changed and conuerted into the bodie and bloud of Chriſt (the formes and ſhewes onely of Bread and Wine remaining: which ſingular and miraculous conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the Church calleth Tranſubſtantiation:) let him be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed. <hi>Con. Trid. Seſs.</hi> 13. <hi>Can.</hi> 2. This their doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, is a very fable to mock fooles withall, and it ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth both the nature and vſe of the Sacrament, <hi>Atterſoll</hi> on the Sacraments, <hi>page</hi> 45. 46. <hi>&amp; page</hi> 365. to 369. If there were a miraculous conuerſion (as they ſay there is) of the Bread and Wine, it would appeare to the outward ſenſes. For al true miracles are wrought openly, cleerely, &amp; euidently to mens
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22743:16"/>
ſenſes, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.26. But the Bread and Wine, by the iudgement of all the ſenſes, remaineth and appeareth to be the ſame in ſubſtance which it was before, of the ſame quality, quantitie, colour, taſte, handling, ſmelling, vertue and nouriſhment: there is not any one ſenſe, or all the ſenſes together, that can iudge otherwiſe of it, then it did before. If a man ſhould bee called in, when the Bread and Wine is ſet on the Table, and bidden to conſider well what he there ſeeth, ſmelleth &amp; taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and then is willed to goe forth, and to come in againe, after the Conſecration is ended by the Prieſt, and to do the like: and then is asked what he thinketh of it: he, no doubt, will anſwere (vnleſſe feare of perſecution make him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale the truth) I ſee, feele, ſmell, and taſte the ſame wafer-cake, and wine that I did before: I can perceiue no naturall and ſubſtantiall change therein. And therefore it followeth, that there is no miracle wrought, and conſequently, no tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation at all. The difference that is, is in the end &amp; vſe onely. Before conſecration, it was common bread and wine, ordained for the nouriſhing of our bodies. After conſecrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, it becommeth holy Bread and Wine, ſanctified by the Lord, not ſo much to feede the body, as the ſoule.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Did not the ancient Fathers hold this doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>They knew nothing hereof, for at leaſt 800. yeeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt. Afterwards begun the diſputations of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, but not approued as an Article of faith. The Church for a whole thouſand yeeres taught no other then ſpirituall receiuing of Chriſt. In the yeere 1215. Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation was decreed and determined in the Councell of Lateran, vnder Pope <hi>Innocent the Third,</hi> and made a maine matter of faith, <hi>Perk.</hi> 2. <hi>vol.</hi> 558, 559.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What ſay you then of their Tranſubſtantiated, or conſecrated hoſt (as it is called) or the bread in the boxe carried in proceſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n &amp; worſhipped?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Surely it is nothing elſe, but a wheaten, or breaden god, or rather an Idol, nothing inferiour to <hi>Aarons</hi> Calfe, or <hi>Ierohoams</hi> Calues, or the <hi>Nehuſtan,</hi> and piece of braſſe that <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:22743:16"/>
brake in pieces: nay, as vile and deteſtable as an Idoll among the Heathen. And for a concluſion of their doctrine of Tranſubſtantiation, I will heere ſet downe a wittie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit which one ſhewed me not long ſince: I haue kept the matter, but changed the meeter, to make it ſound ſomewhat the ſweeter.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>The Prieſts doe make Chriſts body and bloud,</l>
                     <l>Hereof none muſt once doubt:</l>
                     <l>They eate, they drinke, they box him vp,</l>
                     <l>They beare him all about.</l>
                  </q>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 7.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am ſatisfied touching the firſt point, namely, that the Papiſts are not of ſound faith: but how doe you proue that they are not of good life, ſeeing they doe ſo many good workes?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>I proue it thus: Where the Doctrine is corrupt, the life cannot be good: but their doctrine (as you haue heard) is moſt corrupt, therefore their life cannot bee good. A true faith is the ground of a good life, and without which it is impoſſible to pleaſe God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. yea, whatſoeuer is not of faith, is ſinne, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. A true faith they haue not, and therefore their workes cannot be good, and ſuch as may pleaſe God. That they haue not a true and ſound faith, hath bin ſhewed in many particulars, and it further appeareth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in this, that they do euen wilfully reiect the meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is wrought, namely, the preaching, hearing and reading the Word of God. They haue not, neither will they haue the Scriptures to be ſoundly preached, read, and heard in their owne tongue. That they cannot abide to haue them in their owne language, appeareth by this one example<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> One <hi>Pauier</hi> a Towne-Clarke of London (in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth) hearing that the Scriptures ſhould be put into Engliſh, he ſpake to this effect, and confirmed it with an oath: <hi>viz.</hi> that if he knew that the Scriptures ſhould bee put into Engliſh, and that the King would haue them to be read in the Church, rather then he would l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue ſo long to ſee it, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ould cut his owne throat: But (as <hi>Hall</hi> ſaith, who heard
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22743:17"/>
him ſpeake it) he was not ſo good as his word: for, inſtead of cutting his throat, he hanged himſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What is the cauſe that they cannot abide to haue the Scriptures in their owne language?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>S. <hi>John</hi> giues the reaſon. For, euery one that doth euill hateth the light, neither co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to it, left his deeds ſhould be reproued &amp; diſcouered, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.20. If the Owle flieth abroad by day, the birds by &amp; by diſcerne him, follow him, &amp; fall vpon him; and therfore he flies abroad in the night, and then he is quiet. If the Scriptures ſhould be ſuffered to be expounded and read of all Nations in their owne language, then that Owle of <hi>Rome</hi> (the Pope I meane) with all his fooleries and abominations, would be diſcerned and diſcouered, and then the world would hate him, follow after him, &amp; perſecute him, (euen as the ſmall birds doe the Owle:) and therefore they cannot abide the Scriptures in the vulgar tongue, but loue darknes rather then light, becauſe their deedes are euill: <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.19.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What ſay you then to their good works, as building of Churches, giuing of Almes, &amp;c?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Theſe and ſuch like workes, required in the Law of God, in themſelues are good, and to be practiſed of all: but to them they are (as the Fathers called the vertues of the Heathen) but <hi>ſplendida peccata,</hi> glittering droſſe, and beautifull deformities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe they teach any thing contrarie to the morall Law, and to the doctrine of good workes?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, they doe both teach and practiſe many things di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrarie to Gods Commandements. They reach for good workes, ſuch things as are not commanded, but rather forbidden in the Law of God, as namely, to goe on Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, to vow ſingle life, to faſt forty dayes and forty nights<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, concerning ſet Pilgrimages vnto certaine Images there was none of the Fathers did ſo much as dreame of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for 600. yeeres after Chriſt at the leaſt, <hi>Perkins</hi> 2. <hi>Vol. p<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 141, 542.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:22743:17"/>Secondly, the neceſſitie of the vowe of continencie was eſtabliſhed firſt, and annexed vnto Orders, about 380. yeeres after Chriſt, and that by Pope <hi>Siricius.</hi> But it had no vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall admiſſion, vntill the time of Pope <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> in the yeere 1070. <hi>Perkins</hi> 1. Vol. 583. to 587. 2. Volume 575, 576. Acts and Monuments, 1151.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, their doctrine of ſingle life was neuer comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of God, nor knowne in the Primitiue Church, but hath ſprung vp ſince, and is indeede the very doctrine of Diuels, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.13. So is alſo their forbidding of meates for religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſake. They teach alſo, that a man may fulfill the Lawe; yea, doe workes of Supererogation, that is, more then the Lawe doth require: and that men of their abundance, may allot to others ſuch workes of Supererogation, <hi>Rhem. on</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. <hi>ſect.</hi> 6. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3. This doctrine of theirs makes the Law of God to be vnperfect, and is directly contrary to the words of Chriſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 17.10. And it was not knowne of the ancient Fathers. They ſpake indeed ſometimes of Supere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogation, but in a farre other ſence then Papiſts doe. There are no ſuch workes to be found in the perſon of any meere man or Angell, but onely in the perſon of Chriſt, God and man, <hi>Perk.</hi> 1. <hi>vol.</hi> 598. 599. 2. <hi>vol.</hi> 540. 541.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 8.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shew me, I pray you, in particular, what things they teach con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the commandements?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>I could plainely proue vnto you, that they doe both teach and practiſe many things contrary to euery one of the Commandements: but I will onely ſet downe the chiefeſt, and ſuch as moſt men know to be true.</p>
                  <p>The firſt Commandement concernes the inward worſhip of God: the ground of which worſhip is the true knowledge of God; and without which, none can truely worſhip and ſerue him: for ſuch as our knowledge is, ſuch is our worſhip, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.9. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.10. <hi>Ier.</hi> 9.24. The Papiſts teach, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gnorance is the mother of deuotion: but the truth is, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he mother of ſuperſtition and idolatry, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.8. The Papiſts
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22743:18"/>
therefore being ignorant, and without the true knowledge of God, cannot truely worſhip him, but muſt needs bee Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, worſhipping they know not what. The firſt Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment requireth that wee haue the true <hi>Iehoua</hi> for our onely God. They make Chriſts body to be God, becauſe they hold that it may be in many places at once, which thing is proper only to God. They make the Pope to be God, &amp; that in plaine words. <hi>Chriſtopher Marcellus</hi> ſaid to the Pope, Thou art ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God vpon earth: and the Pope tooke it to himſelfe, <hi>Concil. Later. Seſſ.</hi> 4.</p>
                  <p>They giue the power to the Pope, which is proper to God, and ſo make him to be God. As, that he can make holy that which is vnholy, pardon ſinnes, &amp;c. <hi>Perkins</hi> 1. vol. 400. 1. and they giue diuine worſhip to creatures, and ſo make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Gods. The ſecond Commandement concerneth the outward worſhip of God, or the forme &amp; manner of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. This Commandement they haue cleane put out of the Decalogue, and to fill vp the number, they diuide the laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two. The ſcope of this Commandement is, that no I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage is to be made of God, nor any worſhip performed to him in an Image, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.15, 16. But they teach it lawfull to make Images of the true God, and to worſhip him in them, and that there is a religious worſhip due to them, <hi>Belarm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> imag. ſanct. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. And in the ſecond <hi>Nicen</hi> Councell it it was decreed, that the Image of God ſhould be worſhipped with the ſame worſhip that is due vnto God. Their practice is anſwerable to their doctrine: for they worſhip the Images of God, of Chriſt, the Saints, the woodden Croſſe, yea, a piece of bread.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They ſay, that they doe not worſhip the images, but God, Chriſt, and the Saints in the image.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Suppoſe that this were true, yet in ſo doing, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit groſſe idolatry, and the ſame that the people of Iſrae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> did, for which God plagued them greatly, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.5, 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thinke there is none ſo very a Calfe, as to thinke that they did worſhip the Calfe it ſelfe. The Calfe was but a repreſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22743:18"/>
of God; and yet they ſinned greatly in making it, and worſhipping God in it. The Heathen in times paſt could ſay as much for themſelues, concerning their worſhipping of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, as the Papiſts now doe: and yet as they were Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſo are the Papiſts: for as touching their ſuperſtition and idolatry, bloud ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be more like to bloud, or an egge to an egge, then the one of them is to another. The Heathen had for euery Nation and Prouince, ſome peculiar god. Among them, the Elements had their ſeueral gods to rule ouer them. The Heathen had a certain god aſſigned to their cattell. The Heathen had peculiar gods for learning and learned men, and for handi-crafts men. And all theſe haue the Papiſts like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. The Heathen erected Altars, ordained Prieſts to offer ſacrifices, fell downe before their idols, &amp;c. So the Papiſts deck and adorne their images, goe on Pilgrimage to them, fall downe vpon their knees before them, and make their prayers vnto them. And what is all this, but to worſhip the very images themſelues, the which is moſt groſſe idolatry? <hi>Muſculus</hi> on <hi>Pſa.</hi> 16. <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>page</hi> 139. 140, <hi>Virels grounds, pag.</hi> 87. to 92. <hi>Atterſoll</hi> on <hi>Philemon, pag.</hi> 63. 64.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They ſay, that there be degrees of religious worſhip, the higheſt is</hi> latria, <hi>and this is due vnto God: the loweſt is</hi> Dulia, <hi>proper to Saints, &amp;c.</hi> Bellar. de imag. Sanct. lib. 2. cap. 25 <hi>The Scripture acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth one onely kinde of religious worſhip, and that due onely to God,</hi> Math. 4.10. Reu. 22.9. <hi>And this diſtinction of theirs was not known and receiued into the Church, till</hi> 400. <hi>yeeres after Chriſt,</hi> Perk. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ol. page 696. 2. vol. 530.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Was not the making and worſhipping of Images approued of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he ancient Fathers?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>There was no vſe of Images among Chriſtians, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lly in their Churches, for 379. yeeres after Chriſt. Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on of Images was neuer publikely authorized till 788. yeres <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fter Chriſt, in the ſecond Councell of <hi>Nice, Perk.</hi> 1. <hi>vol. page</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6. 2. <hi>vol</hi> 421.</p>
                  <p>If you be diſpoſed to ſee more at large when images firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e vp, how they were forbidden and condemned by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22743:19"/>
Emperours and Councels, and how all that the Papiſts can ſay for them, is anſwered: then read the booke of Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies againſt perill of idolatry: for I know none that hath written more ſoundly, fully, and plainely thereof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe they teach and practiſe any thing elſe againſt the ſecond Commandement?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes: to the right worſhipping of God, there is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a reuerend vſe of the meanes of Gods worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, the which are ſincere prayer, preaching, hearing of Gods Word, and the vſe of the Sacraments. Concerning prayer, it muſt be made with vnderſtanding, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 <hi>ver.</hi> 15. Contrary hereunto is their praying in an vnknown tongue. In the pureſt Churches for the ſpace of 800. yeeres at the leaſt, diuine prayer was neuer performed in a tongue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to the people, <hi>Perk.</hi> 2. <hi>vol.</hi> 557. Concerning the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, they doe not rightly adminiſter and receiue them, but haue added and taken from them at their pleaſure.</p>
                  <p>The helps and furtherances of Gods worſhip are ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two; vowes and faſting. The Papiſts make theſe to be parts of Gods worſhip: yea, they make faſting to be a worke of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to Gods iuſtice, for the temporall puniſhment of ſinne, and a meritorious worke, <hi>Rhem.</hi> on 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7. <hi>Perk.</hi> 1. <hi>vol.</hi> 596. <hi>Synopſis Papiſmi.</hi> The ſixt generall Controuerſie, <hi>queſt.</hi> 3.4. The 19. generall Controuerſie, <hi>queſt.</hi> 8. In a word, all their carnall ceremonies, deuiſed by men, and wherein they place the worſhip of God, are contrary to the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement. The moſt of which ceremonies, they haue bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, partly, from the Iewes, partly from the Gentiles. <hi>Wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> on <hi>Iude, pag.</hi> 215. 216.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 9.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe they teach and practiſe any thing contrary to the Comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dements following?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes: The third Commandement concerneth the gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rifying of Gods name in the whole courſe of our life. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> teach men to giue the glory which is proper to God, to cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, as to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the Pope, &amp;c. They teach it law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22743:19"/>
to ſweare by Saints, and not by God onely. They main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine periury, becauſe they teach with one conſent, that one being examined, may anſwere doubtfully againſt the direct intention of the Examiner, framing another meaning to himſelfe in the doubtfulneſſe of his words. As for example, A man is asked whether he were not ſuch a day at the Maſſe, in ſuch a place? They affirme that hee may ſay no, and ſweare vnto it (although he were at it) reſeruing this to himſelfe; not with purpoſe to reueale it to the Examiner: whereas (in the very Law of nature) he that takes an oath, ſhould ſweare ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the intention of him that hath power to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter an oath: and that in truth, iudgement and righteouſnes, <hi>Ier.</hi> 4.2. They are alſo egregious blaſphemers of Gods name. They haue vttered moſt horrible blaſphemies concerning the Scriptures. See Doctor <hi>Willets</hi> foure pillers of Papiſtry, <hi>pa.</hi> 49. to 61. The fift Commandement requireth ſubiection and obedience to Superiours, and namely, to Kings &amp; Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who are ſupreme and next vnder Chriſt, <hi>Ro.</hi> 13.1, 2. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. They teach that the Pope is ſupreme head ouer all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp;c. that he oweth no ſubiection to Kings and Princes, but hath power to make them, and to put them downe at his pleaſure. The Pope and his Clergie will not be in ſubiection to them, but rather exerciſe Lord-ſhip ouer them The Popes ſupremacie was vnheard of and vnknowne, till the yeere of Chriſt 600. It was firſt broached by the murthering Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Phocas,</hi> at the ambitious deſire of the proud Pope <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, about the yeere 607. And ſince that time, the <hi>Popes</hi> haue ſhewed their intolerable pride, in their behauiour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Princes. The Pope in his writings cals himſelfe, <hi>Seruus ſeruorum Dei,</hi> The ſeruant of Gods ſeruants: but in his actions he will be <hi>Dominus dominorum,</hi> the Lord of Lords: wherein he plainely ſheweth himſelfe to bee that man of ſinne and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, which exalteth himſelfe aboue all that is called God, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. This may be ſhewed by many examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> the Third, did tread vpon the neck of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Frederick</hi> the Firſt, blaſphemouſly abuſing the words of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22743:20"/>
the Pſalme, Thou ſhalt tread vpon the Lion and Adder, &amp;c. Acts and Monuments, <hi>pa.</hi> 185. Pope <hi>Celeſtine</hi> crowned <hi>Henry</hi> the Fift with his foote, and with his foot ſpurned it off again, <hi>ibid.</hi> 221. The Papiſts alſo teach and maintaine diſobedience to Parents: for, they teach that it is lawfull for the child, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Roman Catholike, to deny his duty to his parents bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heretikes. And as the Scribes and Phariſes taught, that if the children did bring to their <hi>Corban,</hi> (that is, their Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury) though they neglected their parents, yet they were free: ſo they teach children to giue that they haue to Monaſteries, &amp;c. wherewith they ſhould relieue their Parents, <hi>Bucanus</hi> Common places, <hi>page</hi> 901.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 10.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Doe they teach and practiſe any thing contrary to the ſixt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, the ſixt commandement forbiddeth vs to kill, or hurt any man. They teach it lawfull for ſubiects not onely to riſe vp againſt, but euen to kill their Princes the Lords An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed (if they be excommunicated by the Pope) and that it is a meritorious worke ſo to doe. This with other ſuch like di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelliſh doctrines, and the Authors thereof, are to be ſeene more at large in <hi>Bucanus</hi> Common places, concerning Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates: and in Maſter <hi>Taylor</hi> on Pſalme 32. <hi>pag.</hi> 208, 209.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can you name any that haue put it in practice?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the Seuenth, called <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> hired one to kill the Emperour. A Monke poiſoned King <hi>Iohn, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the third, King of <hi>France,</hi> was ſlaine by a Frier. Yea, Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> highly commended the Fryer for doing of it. <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth of <hi>France</hi> was alſo ſlaine by a Papiſt. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, (yea of their Prieſts and Ieſuites) haue attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to kill our late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and our King <hi>Iames,</hi> with all his royall Iſſue, and that after a moſt barbarous manner. Theſe Popiſh Traitors may very fitly bee compared to that baſe and vnnaturall bird the Cuckow: who though hee be hatched, fed and brought vp by a little bird, yet he deuoureth both the naturall yong ones, and alſo the damme her ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:22743:20"/>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Are there none that teach and practiſe the killing of Princes bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Papiſts?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>This doctrine was neuer maintained by any Heretikes (beſides the Papiſts) as our moſt Chriſtian and learned King hath ſhewed in a ſpeech of his, vttered in the Parliament houſe, in the yeere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>605. by occaſion of the Gun-powder Treaſon. And herein you may ſee how contrarie they are both to the doctrine &amp; practice of the Prophets, Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, who both taught and practiſed ſubiection, euen to wicked and idolatrous Princes, and did neuer ſo much as attempt to hurt them. As for example: <hi>Saul</hi> was a wicked King, forſaken of God, and one that did moſt cruelly perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute <hi>Dauid,</hi> who was anointed to be King after him. At two ſeuerall times the Lord deliuered <hi>Saul</hi> into his hands, ſo that he might (without any reſiſtance) haue killed him: yea, <hi>Abiſhai</hi> deſired that he might ſtrike him but once with his ſpeare. But what ſaid <hi>Dauid?</hi> Touch him not, for who can lay his hand on the Lords anointed, and be guiltleſſe? Nay, his heart ſmote him for cutting off the skirt of <hi>Sauls</hi> Robe, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.4, 5, 6. <hi>&amp;c. chap.</hi> 26.8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And afterwards, when one brought ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to <hi>Dauid</hi> that he had ſlaine <hi>Saul,</hi> what did <hi>Dauid?</hi> Did he commend him for it, as the Pope did the Frier? No, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to be ſlaine for his labour, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.14, 15, 16. Now what thinke you of <hi>Dauid?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hee was a man after Gods owne heart, indued with the Spirit of God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>It is moſt true: and therefore the Papiſts (which both teach and practiſe the contrary) are indued with the Spirit of Satan. S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that to forbid marriage and meates, is a doctrine of diuels, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 3. If that bee a doctrine of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, then much more is this. In the ſixt Commandement is alſo condemned all crueltie: yet herein they exceed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell all others. And this is a ſpeciall note of a falſe Religion; and yet this is one ſpeciall meanes whereby Popery is vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held. See <hi>Tailor</hi> on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. <hi>p.</hi> 204. to 208. <hi>Salomon</hi> deſcribes an Harlot by three properties, cruelty, treachery, and flattery,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:22743:21"/>
                     <hi>Pro.</hi> 2.16, 17, 18. As a diſhoneſt and vnchaſte woman is thus diſcerned, ſo is a corrupt religion. And theſe are the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>adges and enſignes of the Whore of <hi>Babylon:</hi> Where they get the ſword, they ſhew all cruelty: where their power fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth, they worke by trechery: where this ſpeedeth not, they will deceiue by flattery and hypocriſie. See the Preface to Doctor <hi>Willets</hi> Treatiſe on the Epiſtle of S. <hi>Iude, page</hi> 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 11.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What doe they teach and practiſe contrary to the ſeuenth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>They hold and teach, that marriage is vnlawfull in the Clergie: and that the marriage of Miniſters is the worſt ſort of incontinency and fornication, <hi>Rhem.</hi> on 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Sect.</hi> 8. whereas marriage is the remedy againſt fornication, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.2. They allow their Prieſts to keepe harlots, (ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to marry) ſo they doe it cloſely: for this caueat is giuen them: <hi>Si non caſte, tamen cautè.</hi> If thou canſt not liue chaſtely, thou maiſt keepe a whore warily. And what vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and filthineſſe hath bin committed by many Popes and Popiſh prieſts, all the world knoweth. A taſte hereof, I will giue you in a few examples.</p>
                  <p>Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the 13. was an Adulterer, and an inceſtuous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Being found without the City with another mans wife, he was ſo wounded of her husband, that within eight dayes after he died, Acts and Monuments, <hi>page</hi> 143. Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth erected at Rome a Stewes of double abomination, not onely of women; but alſo of men, <hi>ibid.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 667. <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt committed inceſt with his owne daughter <hi>Lucretia, Guicciardine lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Jnnocentius</hi> the eighth had diuers baſtards, and boaſted of them. See <hi>Willet</hi> on <hi>Iude, page</hi> 188. They had one Pope that did beget no child, but was begotten with child, and brought it forth in going on proceſſion: and that was Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the eighth, who proued to be <hi>Joane,</hi> and not <hi>Iohn.</hi> This they deny, but there was of late yeeres written a booke by M. <hi>Alexander Cooke:</hi> and another written in Latine
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22743:21"/>
by a ſtranger, wherein they proue (and that out of Popiſh Writers) that there was ſuch a one. For they ſufficiently proue themſelues to be men indeed, in begetting Baſtards. It is an old ſaying, It muſt needs be a holy Proceſſion, where the Diuell beares the Croſſe: ſo it muſt needs bee an holy, chaſte and pure Church, that hath ſuch vnholy, impure, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſte, and filthy heads, as many Popes haue been. And as were the heads, ſuch was the reſt of the body. Their Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries and Monkiſh Cels were detected of moſt infamous inceſts, fornications, &amp;c. as doth appeare in the inquiſition made in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, <hi>Praefat. Balaei. de actis Roman. Pontif.</hi> See a little booke (lately ſet forth) called the Friers Chronicle. Contrary to the eighth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are the Popes Buls, Indulgences and pardons for ſinnes and all for money. They ſell ſuch things as are not to bee ſold, namely, remiſſion of ſinnes, and the merits by which men may come to the Kingdome of Heauen. But no penny, no <hi>Pater-noſter, Synopſis Papiſmi. Controuerſie</hi> 14. <hi>part.</hi> 3. Popes Buls and Indulgences (wherein is giuen abſolution from the guilt of temporall puniſhment) were not knowne to the Catholike Church, for 1000. yeeres and more after Chriſt, <hi>Perk.</hi> 2. <hi>vol.</hi> 589. And herein they maintaine licenciouſneſſe: for what neede one care what ſinne hee committeth, when for a little money he may haue a Pardon for it?</p>
                  <p>One <hi>Roger Holland</hi> (ſometime a Papiſt) ſaith thus, I was of this your blind religion; hauing liberty vnder your auricular confeſſion, I made no conſcience of ſinne, but truſted to the Prieſts abſolution; he alſo for money, doing ſome penance for me: which after I had giuen, I cared no further what of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences I did: no more then he cared, after he had my money, whether he faſted with bread or water for mee or no, Acts and Monuments, <hi>pa.</hi> 2040.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 12.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shew me alſo, I pray you, what they teach and practiſe contrarie to the two laſt Commandements.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>The ninth Commandement condemnes all lying, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:22743:22"/>
diſſimulation, railing, mocking, &amp;c. They maintaine equiuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, which (as the Secular Prieſts haue ſaid) (<hi>Quodlibet</hi> 3. <hi>Art.</hi> 4. <hi>page</hi> 6.) you may terme in plaine Engliſh, lying, and cogging. They are notorious lyers, and ſlanderers, raylers and mockers, <hi>Willet</hi> on <hi>Iude p.</hi> 195. &amp; 205. 212. They haue fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified mens writings, putting in, and putting out what they pleaſe, as is to be ſeene in their <hi>Index expurgatorius.</hi> See <hi>Perk.</hi> 2. <hi>vol. page</hi> 489, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>There haue been in times paſt games appointed for lying. If there were any ſuch now, the Papiſts would carry the whet-ſtone from all the Heretikes in Chriſtendome. The tenth Commandement condemneth originall corruption, and the very euill thoughts and luſts of the heart without conſent.</p>
                  <p>They teach, that concupiſcence in it ſelfe is not ſinne. Theſe are the very words of the Councell of Trent: This concupiſcence (which the Apoſtle ſometime calleth ſinne) the holy <hi>Synod</hi> declareth, that the Catholike Church did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnderſtand to be called ſinne, becauſe it is truely &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſinne in the regenerate, but becauſe it commeth of ſinne, and inclineth vnto ſinne: If any man thinke the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie, let him be accurſed, <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>de pecc. orig.</hi> Wherein they both decree againſt the Apoſtle himſelfe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.23. and alſo they gaine ſay themſelues: for if this concupiſcence boile out of originall ſinne, as out of a fountaine, and that is damnable: it followeth, that concupiſcence or luſt is alſo ſinne before God, and doth deſerue condemnation. They ſay that in the regenerate it is veniall. But this is an vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted principle, that all ſinnes in themſelues and their owne nature are mortall. And concerning this veniall ſinne, it was not knowne among the Fathers for 700. yeeres after Chriſt. And thus you ſee, what groſſe things they both teach and practiſe contrary to the Commandements of God: whereby it plainely appeareth, that Popery cannot bee of God: for thus I reaſon: Whatſoeuer religion doth teach things contrary to the Commandements of God, is not of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:22743:22"/>
God: but Poperie doth ſo, and therefore it is not of GOD: and ſo by good conſequence, Papiſts cannot be good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 13.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hitherto you haue ſhewed, that the Papiſts teach many things contrary to the Creede, the Sacraments, and the ten Commandements, now tell me, I pray you, whether they teach any thing contrary to the Lords Prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>They doe likewiſe teach &amp; practiſe many things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie thereunto, I will but onely name ſome of them. The Lords Prayer teacheth vs to call vpon God only. They teach and practiſe prayer to Saints. In the firſt Petition, we pray for the hallowing of Gods Name. They giue vnto Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, that which is proper to God, and ſo diſhonour Gods Name. In the ſecond petition, we pray for the erecting of Gods Kingdome of grace in our hearts, and alſo for the meanes thereof, namely, the preaching &amp; hearing of Gods Word. They hinder the comming of Gods Kingdome, in reiecting the Word of God, and in perſecuting ſuch as will preach, heare, and reade it. Contrary to the third petition is their doctrine of free-will. Contrary to the fifth petition is their doctrine of ſatisfaction for ſin. In the ſixth petition, we pray for ſtrength to withſtand Satan &amp; his temptations. They teach people to driue away the Diuell with holy-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſuch like childiſh toyes. Theſe and other ſuch like things, they teach and practiſe contrary to the Lords Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 14.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If Popery be ſo contrary to the grounds of Religion, then we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ot ioyne with the Papiſts in their profeſsion?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true indeede: we muſt therefore doe as the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>de <hi>Ieremy (Chap.</hi> 15.19.) Let them returne to thee, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urne not thou to them. We may ioyne with them in reſpect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f ciuill ſocietie, but not in reſpect of Religion: and yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en then we are to take heed, left we be corrupted by them: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r he that toucheth Pitch, ſhall be defiled therewith. Some
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:22743:23"/>
thinke that our Religion, and the religion of the preſent Church of Rome, are all one for ſubſtance, and that they may be vnited: but they are groſely deceiued: for an vnion of theſe two Religions can neuer be made, more then the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of light and darkneſſe, and that becauſe the Church of Rome (as hath at large bin ſhewed) hath ſtrooke at the very foundation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If Poperie bee ſo contrary to the very grounds of Religion, then, what is the cauſe that ſo many (yea, of the more wiſe and learned ſort) do embrace and cleaue to it?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>One ſpeciall cauſe of it is, that becauſe men will not receiue the loue of the Trueth, therefore God will ſend them ſtrong deluſion, that they ſhould beleeue a lie, 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10, 11.</p>
                  <p>A ſecond cauſe is, ignorance of the Scriptures, and of the grounds of Religion, for if men would well acquaint them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues herewith, they ſhould eaſily ſee the groſſeneſſe of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie.</p>
                  <p>A third cauſe is, that Popery is very agreeable and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to mans corrupt nature: As for example: to be iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our good works: to haue images to worſhip God in: to liue in ignorance: to haue pardons for our ſinnes: to ſerue God in outward ceremonies, as in choice of meate, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of dayes, &amp;c. theſe are things very agreeable &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to our corrupt nature, and therefore one eſpeciall cauſe why ſo many embrace Popery.</p>
                  <p>A fourth cauſe is, the tyranny of the Church of Rome, whoſe chiefe meanes to vphold her religion, is fire &amp; ſword for were it not for this, many thouſands in a few yeers would vtterly renounce Popery.</p>
                  <p>A fifth cauſe why ſo many (eſpecially of the Learned) d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> embrace it, is pompe and profit: that is, ambition and coue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>touſneſſe.</p>
                  <p>This was that which made the Scribes and Phariſes (eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> againſt their owne knowledge) to withſtand Chriſt and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Goſpell.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:22743:23"/>And this makes many learned Papiſts ro do the like. They know (no doubt) that in ſome things they erre: as it doth appeare by the words of <hi>Stephen Gardiner</hi> on his death bed.</p>
                  <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> ſeeing him to be in a deſperate caſe, comforteth him with the hope of remiſſion of ſinnes by the merits of Chriſt. <hi>Gardiner</hi> hereunto anſwereth thus: What, will you open that gappe now? you may ſpeake it to me, and to ſuch as are in my caſe: but if you teach it to the people, then farewell all; meaning our authority, pompe, and profit by abſolutions, Maſſes, &amp;c. Theſe are the ſpeciall cauſes why ſo many embrace Popery.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There is one thing more that I would gladly know concerning the Papiſts, and that is, whether a Papist may be ſaued, ſeeing that Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ie is ſo contrary to the grounds of Religion?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>You are then to marke what a Papiſt is. A Papiſt (as the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> on <hi>Acts</hi> 11. <hi>Sect.</hi> 4. doe deſcribe him) is one that cleaueth to the Pope in Religion, and is obedient to him in all things.</p>
                  <p>Euery one now that is vnder the iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Pope, is not to be counted a Papiſt: for there are ſome euen in <hi>Italy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>paine, &amp;c.</hi> that hold the Grounds of Religion, doe ſigh and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rone vnder the Romiſh yoke, and deſire to be free'd from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, yea, would reioyce to ſee it.</p>
                  <p>Againe, there may be ſome, that (for want of knowledge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd the meanes thereof) are entangled with ſome points of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>opery, but yet they hold the foundation, which is CHRIST <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ESVS, and looke to be ſaued by his merits, and not by their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>wne, or any others. Such we account not Papiſts, but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Church and children of GOD. But by Papiſts, wee meane ſuch as cleaue faſt to the Pope in Religion, are in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ings obedient to him, will not be reclaimed from their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>urs, refuſe to heare the Word of God, to read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>res, or any other good bookes. Of ſuch we may boldly ſay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t if they thus continue to the end, they cannot be ſaued.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 15.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I doe now plainely ſee that Papiſts are no good Catholikes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:22743:24"/>
they are neither of ſound faith, nor good life: but tell me (I pray you) who indeed are the true Church, and true Catholikes?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>All that doe truely and ſincerely embrace, profeſſe, and practiſe the aforeſaid grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Religion, in what Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey ſoeuer they liue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Is the Church of England the true Church?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, for it hath the ſpeciall markes of the true Church namely, the Word of God ſincerely and ſoundly preached and the Sacraments rightly adminiſtred.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Papiſts ſay, that there are diuerſiities of opinions among v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> that we cannot agree among our ſelues, and that therefore wee are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the true Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>In all ſubſtantiall points of Religion we agree both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelues, and alſo with all other ſound Proteſtants in Chriſtendome. In other things there haue bin, are, and will be diuerſities of opinions and differences to the worlds end. They ſhould firſt plucke out the beame of their owne eyes: for we can truely charge them with greater differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: As namely, with that ſharpe and bloudy contention betweene the Franciſcans and the Dominicans; and vvith the late bitter contention betweene the Ieſuites and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cular Prieſts: wherein the Prieſts did write as bitterly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Ieſuites (and namely, againſt <hi>Parſons</hi>) as euer did any Proteſtant: nay there was neuer any Proteſtant Write<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that did lay ſuch foule &amp; odious crimes to their charge, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Prieſts did. And heerein they verified the old Prouerbe When theeues fall by the eares, true men come to haue the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> goods. For one diſſention that is among vs, they haue (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> leaſt) ten among themſelues. <hi>Doctor Willet</hi> (in his fourth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler of Papiſtry) hath ſet downe at large:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the conradictions and diuerſe opinions of old Papi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> and new.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The contradictions of the Ieſuites anongſt themſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that their ſtouteſt Champion, <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> is at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riance with himſelfe, ſhamefully forgetting himſelfe, ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and vnſaying: now of one opinion, by and by of anoth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:22743:24"/>
And no maruell. <hi>Oportet enim mendacem eſſe memorem.</hi> A lyer had need to haue a good memory.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, he ſheweth the repugnances, inconueniences, and inconſequent opinions which Popiſh Religion hath in it ſelfe. And thus you ſee, how they charge vs with that, wherein themſelues are moſt faulty.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="dialogue">
               <head>DIALOGVE 16.</head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Are there none among vs, that maintaine any ſtrange and new opinions, contrary to the grounds of Religion?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>If there be any ſuch, our Church doth not approue of them, but rather cenſure and puniſh them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There be ſome that profeſſe the former grounds of Religion as we doe, and yet ſay that there is no true Church among vs: and therefore will not ioyne with vs in prayers, hearing the Word, and in the vſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>acraments, but ſeparate themſelues from vs: what ſay you of ſuch?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſay, that they are poſſeſſed with the ſpirit of pride and ſingularity; and that in ſo doing, they doe euen deny <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heſe Articles of faith, the Catholike Church, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, and are ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpeakes of, <hi>Ro.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25, 39. <hi>Maſter Perkins</hi> (in his firſt Vol. <hi>pag.</hi> 409.) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls them a ſchiſmaticall and vndiſcreet company, and ſaith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at they are full of pride, thinking themſelues to bee full, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hen they are empty; to haue all knowledge, when they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>norant, &amp; haue need to be catechized. Another ſaith thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> them: The errour of thoſe men is full of euill, yea of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>emie, who doe in ſuch manner make a departure from this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hurch, as if Chriſt were quite baniſhed from hence, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at there could be no hope of ſaluation to thoſe that abide <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ere. And further he ſaith, that if they cannot finde Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere, they ſhall finde him no where. The errours of theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n you may ſee in a little Treatiſe ſet forth by M. <hi>Bernard,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>led, The <hi>Separatiſts Schiſme.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I pray ſhew me ſome example, that they ought not to ſeparate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>mſelues from vs, and that they doe ſinne in ſo doing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>In the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> the inceſtuous man was not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>niſhed: fornication was lightly regarded, yea there were
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:22743:25"/>
ſome that euen denied the Reſurrection, yet S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and call them the Church and Saints: hee doth not perſwade any to make a ſeparation, but doth plainely rebuke them, and ſheweth how they ſhould puniſh the euill doer. I ſpeake not this to excuſe any groſſe ſinne that raigneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs: (for I wiſh that the ſame might bee ſeuerely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed) but to ſhew, that where the Word is truely preached and the Sacraments rightly adminiſtred (as in our Church they are) none ought for any cauſe to ſeparate themſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And, that ſuch as doe it, doe ſinne grieuouſly, I will ſhew yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by a familiar example. A mother conceiueth and bringeth forth a ſonne, and that with great trauaile and paine: She<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> traineth him vp to mans eſtate, and that not without great care and labour: This ſonne at length eſpying ſome ſpot and blemiſh, or ſome infirmitie in his mother, forſaketh her, and will not acknowledge her to be his mother, what would you now thinke of him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Surely I ſhould thinke ſuch a one to be a very wicked and vnna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſonne.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen ſuch are they, who (for ſome ſeeming faults i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our Church) deny it to be a true Church, and doe ſeparat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> themſelues from it: whereas this Church hath conceiue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them, brought them forth, and nouriſhed them. For if e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they were truely begotten vnto Chriſt, and borne anew, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hath been by our Church, and our Miniſterie, by whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> likewiſe they haue been trained vp, and brought to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> knowledge which they haue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There are many amongſt vs that make great profeſsion of R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, but I can ſee no good workes come from them: nay, they are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> onely barren in good workes, but alſo liue in ſome one groſſe ſinne or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Are theſe the true Church, and true Catholikes?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Though they liue in the Church, yet they are no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Church: they are but Hypocrites, and ſhal (if they rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> not) haue the reward of Hypocrites: yea it ſhall bee e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in the Day of Iudgement for many Papiſts, then for the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> becauſe by their barten and fruitleſſe, yea wicked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:22743:25"/>
they haue cauſed the Name of God, his Goſpell, &amp; the true Profeſſors thereof, to be euil ſpoken of. Let all therfore that will be accounted the true Church, and true Chriſtians, be carefull to adorne the doctrine of God our Sauiour in all things, and that by a godly conuerſation, and by doing of good workes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>C.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The name of God be bleſſed for this our conference, whereby I finde my ſelfe much edified. There remaineth yet one thing more, which I will demand of you: and that is, How I may come to know and be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that I am indeed a member of the true Church, and that I ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be ſaued?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M.</speaker>
                  <p>Be diligent to heare the Word of God preached. Reade the Scriptures. Receiue often the Sacrament. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint your ſelfe throughly with the aforeſaid grounds of Religion. Ioyne hereunto earneſt and hearty prayer. Set a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part ſome time for theſe things, ſpecially be carefull to ſpend the Sabbath herein. And to all theſe things ioyne an holy conuerſation, indeuouring aboue all things to haue alway a cleere conſcience toward God, and toward men. In doing this, you ſhall at length come to that full aſſurance, whereof S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh, namely, that you are the child of God, and that nothing ſhall be able to ſeparate you from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <epigraph>
            <q>Babylon is falne, is falne;
<bibl>
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 14.8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Praiſe, honour, glory and power, be vnto him that ſitteth vpon the Throne, and vnto the Lambe for euermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Reuelation 5.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
         </epigraph>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
